[
    {
        "question": " Netscape NavigatorB. Mozilla FirefoxC. MosaicD. Google Chrome",
        "options": [
            "1. C, A, B, D",
            "2. A, B, D, C",
            "3. B, A, C, D",
            "4. A, B, C, D"
        ],
        "answer": "1. C, A, B, D"
    },
    {
        "question": " RIF and SWRLB. UNICODE and URIC. OWLD. XMLE. RDF",
        "options": [
            "1. C, B, A, D, E",
            "2. A, D, B, E, C",
            "3. B, D, E, C, A",
            "4. D, B, A, E, C"
        ],
        "answer": "3. B, D, E, C, A"
    },
    {
        "question": "05, 0.035, 0.025, 0.01 and 0.00 respectively.A. 80B. 94C, 89D. 100E. 99",
        "options": [
            "1. B. D, E, A, C",
            "2. D, B, A, C, E",
            "3. C, A, E, B, D",
            "4. A, C, B, E, D"
        ],
        "answer": "4. A, C, B, E, D"
    },
    {
        "question": " Brief summaryB. Statistical analysisC. Areas for future researchD. Research procedureE. Objective of the study",
        "options": [
            "1. E, B, D, A, C",
            "2. C, A, B, E, D",
            "3. A, E, D, B, C",
            "4. B, C, A, D, E"
        ],
        "answer": "3. A, E, D, B, C"
    },
    {
        "question": " Arrange them in reverse chronological order of their foundationA. All India Council for Technical Education (AICTE)B. National Council of Educational Research and Training (NCERT)C. National Institute of Educational Planning and Administration (NIEPA)D. State Council of Educational Research and Training (SCERT Delht) E. University Grants Commission (UGC)",
        "options": [
            "1. A, B, C, D, E",
            "2. D, C, B, E, A",
            "3. A, E, B, C, D",
            "4. D, B, A, C, E"
        ],
        "answer": "2. D, C, B, E, A"
    },
    {
        "question": " Information is a property of dataB. Product of human brainC. Information may be abstract or concreteD. Information can not be creativeE. Information is personal knowledge",
        "options": [
            "1.B, C and D only",
            "2. A,B and C only",
            "3. A, C and D only",
            "4.B, C and E only"
        ],
        "answer": "2. A,B and C only"
    },
    {
        "question": "A. Researchers shall be asked to submit a revised scriptB. Researchers be asked to pay a penalty of Rs.5000/-C. Researchers shall be debarred from submitting a revised scriptD. Researchers registration for the research degree shall be cancelledE. After there unsatisfactory plagiarism reports bailable arrest warrant will be issued.",
        "options": [
            "1. A, Band C only",
            "2. A.C and E only",
            "3. A, C and D only",
            "4.B, C and E only"
        ],
        "answer": "3. A, C and D only"
    },
    {
        "question": "A. Nalanda University was established in qth century B.C.B. Area of library was called Dharma GanjaC. Library was housed in three grand buildingsD. The buildings were named as Ratna-Sagar, Ratna Pithika and Ratna RanjakaE. Ratna Ranjaka was a nine storied building",
        "options": [
            "1. A, C and D only",
            "2. B, C and D only",
            "3. A,B and E only",
            "4.B,C and E only"
        ],
        "answer": "4.B,C and E only"
    },
    {
        "question": " Needs a specialized knowledgeB. Requires set of principles of professional ethicsC. Information work 1s distinct from librarianship says FarradaneD. Mainly an activity involving service against fee or feesE. The term information specialist does not include library professional",
        "options": [
            "1. A,B and C only",
            "2. B, C and D only",
            "3. C, D and E only",
            "4.B, D and E only"
        ],
        "answer": "1. A,B and C only"
    },
    {
        "question": " CAS Registry is a factual data baseB. CAS is a bibliographic data baseC. PubMed is a full text data baseD. ERIC is a numeric data baseE. SCOPUS 1s a citation database",
        "options": [
            "1.B, C and D only",
            "2. A, C and E only",
            "3. C, D and E only",
            "4. A,B and D only"
        ],
        "answer": "2. A, C and E only"
    },
    {
        "question": "Sequence the following Acts enacted by the Government of India logically from the date of their first enactment:A. The Geographical Indications of Goods (Registration and Protection) ActB. The Patents ActC. The Designs ActD. The Trade and Merchandise Act",
        "options": [
            "1. A, B, C, D",
            "2. B, C, D, A",
            "3. B, D, A, C",
            "4. C, D, A, B"
        ],
        "answer": "1. A, B, C, D"
    },
    {
        "question": "In what sequence should one consult the following information sources to understand about \"Referral Service\" with its increasing extension and intention:A. Library Science with a Slant to DocumentationB. Reference Service by S.R. RanganathanC. Harrod's Librarian's Glossary and Reference BookD. Encyclopedia of Library and Information Science",
        "options": [
            "1. A, C, D, B",
            "2. B, C, D, A",
            "3. C, D, B, A",
            "4. D, B, A, C"
        ],
        "answer": "1. A, C, D, B"
    },
    {
        "question": "\tArrange the following steps of the information literacy scope and sequence model in the logical sequence of their operation:A. FindB. AssessC. CreateD. QuestionE. Gather",
        "options": [
            "1. A, B, C, D, E",
            "2. D, A, E,C, B",
            "3. D, E, A, B, C",
            "4. B, D, A, C, E"
        ],
        "answer": "2. D, A, E,C, B"
    },
    {
        "question": "\tArrange the following Year Books and Directories in ascending order from oldest to latest of their first publication:A. Europa World YearbookB. Demographic YearbookC. World of LearningD. Commonwealth Universities Yearbook",
        "options": [
            "1. A, B, C, D",
            "2. D, C, B, A",
            "3. B, C, A, D",
            "4. A, D, C, B"
        ],
        "answer": "3. B, C, A, D"
    },
    {
        "question": "\tInformation communication processes can be classified broadly into the following four categories in terms of its level. Arrange them in decreasing level of involvement of the number of people in the process:A. Interpersonal CommunicationB. Intrapersonal CommunicationC. Group CommunicationD. Mass Communication",
        "options": [
            "1.  A, B, C, D",
            "2. D, C, A, B",
            "3. D, C, A, B",
            "4. B, A, C, D"
        ],
        "answer": "1.  A, B, C, D"
    },
    {
        "question": "With specific reference to the establishment year, arrange the following consortia in ascending order:A. INDESTB. FORSAC. National Knowledge Research Consortium (NERC)D. NGC-DAE Consortium",
        "options": [
            "1. A, B, C, D",
            "2. B, C, D, A",
            "3. B, D, A, C",
            "4. D, B, A, C"
        ],
        "answer": "2. B, C, D, A"
    },
    {
        "question": "\tArrange the steps used in POPSI in the logical sequence:A. Content AnalysisB. AlphabetisationC. ModulationD. Preparation of entriesE. Formalisation",
        "options": [
            "1. A, E, C, D, B",
            "2. E, A, D, C, B",
            "3. B, A, D, C, E",
            "4. A, B, C, D, E"
        ],
        "answer": "4. A, B, C, D, E"
    },
    {
        "question": "\tTreatment for cancer in India arrange the concepts of this title using facet sequence formula of Dr. S.R RanganathanA. TreatmentB. MedicineC. IndiaD. DiseaseE. Cancer",
        "options": [
            "1. A, B, D, E, C",
            "2. D, A, E, C, \u0412",
            "3. E, C, D, B, A",
            "4. B, D, E, A, C"
        ],
        "answer": "3. E, C, D, B, A"
    },
    {
        "question": "Arrange the steps of performance appraisal in proper sequence.A. Performance improvement planningB. Compensation and rewarding good performanceC. Performance feedback and evaluation D. Potential appraisalE. Performance reviewing or progress review",
        "options": [
            "1. A, B, D, C, E",
            "2. E, C, B, D, A",
            "3. D, C, A, B, E",
            "4. B, C, A, D, E"
        ],
        "answer": "2. E, C, B, D, A"
    },
    {
        "question": "Arrange the steps of PERT/CPM tn chronological order.A. Determine the earliest and latest feasible event timesB. Identify the precedence relationships among the activitiesC. Identify activities required by the project D. Determine the expected time requirement for each activityD. Develop a network diagram of activities and events or nodes showing precedence relationships",
        "options": [
            "1. E, B, D, A, C",
            "2. C, B, D, E, A",
            "3. B, C, E, D, A",
            "4. D, A, E, B, C"
        ],
        "answer": "3. B, C, E, D, A"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is a computer program used to search website content and index, over the internet?",
        "options": [
            "Search Engine",
            "Web Browser",
            "Web Crawler",
            "Meta Search Engine"
        ],
        "answer": "Web Crawler"
    },
    {
        "question": "Tags in eXtensible Markup Language are case-sensitive because:",
        "options": [
            "These tags are fixed by the W3C",
            "These tags are pre-defined",
            "These tags are standardized already",
            "These tags are user-defined"
        ],
        "answer": "These tags are user-defined"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the early 1980s, the UGC established National Information Centers and Inter-University Centers to render reference and documentation services for promoting research in existing Institutes/Universities. Which of the following Universities had got an inter-university center?",
        "options": [
            "Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore",
            "Maharaja Sayajirao University, Baroda",
            "SNDT Women's University, Bombay",
            "Jawaharlal Nehru University, New Delhi"
        ],
        "answer": "Jawaharlal Nehru University, New Delhi"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was not a member of the UGC panel on Library and Information Science for the Curriculum Development Committee 2001 headed by Prof. C.R. Karisiddappa?",
        "options": [
            "Prof. Harsha Parekh, SNDT Women's University",
            "Prof. T. Vishwanathan, INSDOC",
            "Prof. P.S.G. Kumar, RTM Nagpur University",
            "Prof. M.K.R. Naidu, M.S. University"
        ],
        "answer": "Prof. P.S.G. Kumar, RTM Nagpur University"
    },
    {
        "question": "In which year, Delhi Public Library had introduced the mobile service for readers?",
        "options": [
            "1951 AD",
            "1953 AD",
            "1972 AD",
            "1996 AD"
        ],
        "answer": "1953 AD"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is not a digital library initiative?",
        "options": [
            "Google Books Library Project",
            "Digital Library Federation (DLF)",
            "Web Library Project",
            "Million Book Project"
        ],
        "answer": "Digital Library Federation (DLF)"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the technology drives are not part of the SMAC system?",
        "options": [
            "Social Media",
            "Mobile Computing",
            "Data Analytics",
            "CMS"
        ],
        "answer": "CMS"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the full form of ROMEO in Sherpa ROMEO?",
        "options": [
            "Record of Master file for Open Archiving",
            "Rights of Master Metadata file for Open Archiving",
            "Record Metadata for Open Archiving",
            "Rights Metadata for Open Archiving"
        ],
        "answer": "Rights Metadata for Open Archiving"
    },
    {
        "question": "Laney described the characteristics of:",
        "options": [
            "Geospatial Data",
            "Linked Data",
            "Qualitative Data",
            "Big Data"
        ],
        "answer": "Big Data"
    },
    {
        "question": "SHERNI of Information and Library Network is the expert profile network system that:",
        "options": [
            "Connects the knowledge, skills, and expertise of women across the field of Science, Humanities, Engineering only",
            "Connects the knowledge, skills, and expertise of women across the field of Library and Information Science only",
            "Connects the knowledge, skills, and expertise of women across the various fields of studies only",
            "Connects the knowledge, skills, and expertise of women across the Social Science and Engineering only"
        ],
        "answer": "Connects the knowledge, skills, and expertise of women across the field of Library and Information Science only"
    },
    {
        "question": "If all non-critical activities start as early as possible, the spare time is the:",
        "options": [
            "Latest Finishing Time",
            "Free Float",
            "Total Float",
            "Independent Float"
        ],
        "answer": "Free Float"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is not a principle of library expenditure?",
        "options": [
            "Principle of Economy",
            "Principle of Maximum Aggregate Benefit",
            "Principle of Advance Planning",
            "Principle of Demand and Supply"
        ],
        "answer": "Principle of Demand and Supply"
    },
    {
        "question": "An estimate of loss of a few stacks of a library that is made on the basis of thorough checking is known as:",
        "options": [
            "Stock taking by shelf register",
            "Sample stock verification",
            "Stock taking by master record",
            "Stock taking by Duplicate set of Book cards"
        ],
        "answer": "Sample stock verification"
    },
    {
        "question": "In [job evaluation], actual incidents relevant to the work situation are taken into account, and each employee is made to answer each incident to his supervisor.",
        "options": [
            "Informal Plan Method",
            "Self Rating Method",
            "Mutual Rating Method",
            "Critical Plan Method"
        ],
        "answer": "Critical Plan Method"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following data collection tools is concerned with broad underlying feelings of an individual's life experience?",
        "options": [
            "Focused Interview",
            "Non-directive Interview",
            "Clinical Interview",
            "Telephonic Interview"
        ],
        "answer": "Clinical Interview"
    },
    {
        "question": "The statistical test used to investigate the differences among the means of all the populations simultaneously is:",
        "options": [
            "T-test",
            "ANOVA",
            "Correlation analysis",
            "Chi-square test"
        ],
        "answer": "ANOVA"
    },
    {
        "question": "The preliminary part of the research report may not include:",
        "options": [
            "Table of Contents",
            "List of tables",
            "Preface",
            "Importance of the problem under investigation"
        ],
        "answer": "Importance of the problem under investigation"
    },
    {
        "question": "Probability distribution of all the possible means of random samples of a given sample size refers to:",
        "options": [
            "Sampling distribution of mean",
            "Distribution of sample",
            "Distribution of population",
            "Probability distribution of sample"
        ],
        "answer": "Sampling distribution of mean"
    },
    {
        "question": "One nibble equals to how many bits?",
        "options": [
            "6",
            "4",
            "8",
            "2"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "A bidirectional wireless system that transmits data via LED or infrared light is:",
        "options": [
            "Wi-Fi",
            "Li-Fi",
            "Mobile communication",
            "V-SAT"
        ],
        "answer": "Li-Fi"
    },
    {
        "question": "Reader's Digest is an example of:",
        "options": [
            "Scholarly journal",
            "Trade journal",
            "Popular/General interest periodical",
            "Current source of information"
        ],
        "answer": "Popular/General interest periodical"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is the author of \"Basic Reference Sources\"?",
        "options": [
            "S.R. Ranganathan",
            "Louis Shores",
            "Dennis Grogan",
            "Margaret Hutchins"
        ],
        "answer": "Louis Shores"
    },
    {
        "question": "The term \"Reprography\" was first introduced in:",
        "options": [
            "India",
            "Italy",
            "Turkey",
            "Germany"
        ],
        "answer": "Germany"
    },
    {
        "question": "Webcasting is an example of:",
        "options": [
            "Internet Technology",
            "Web Technology",
            "Push Technology",
            "Communication Technology"
        ],
        "answer": "Push Technology"
    },
    {
        "question": "CERL stands for:",
        "options": [
            "Consortium of European Research Libraries",
            "Community for European Research Libraries",
            "Consortium for East Asia Research Libraries",
            "Collection of European Research Libraries"
        ],
        "answer": "Consortium of European Research Libraries"
    },
    {
        "question": "A single schedule that lists all of the simple and compound subjects together with their ready-made class numbers is called:",
        "options": [
            "Faceted Classification",
            "Analytico-Synthetic Classification",
            "Knowledge Classification",
            "Enumerative Classification"
        ],
        "answer": "Enumerative Classification"
    },
    {
        "question": "The surviving term of an Expressive Title is denoted by:",
        "options": [
            "Supportive Term",
            "Apparatus Term",
            "Kernel Term",
            "Fanciful Term"
        ],
        "answer": "Kernel Term"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is not a limitation of chain indexing?",
        "options": [
            "Chain indexing depends only on class numbers",
            "Only the last link is specific",
            "False or Unsought link",
            "It provides an alternative approach to the classified file through reverse rendering"
        ],
        "answer": "It provides an alternative approach to the classified file through reverse rendering"
    },
    {
        "question": "Acyclic recurrence of fundamental categories in the facet analysis of a subject is called:",
        "options": [
            "Levels",
            "Rounds",
            "Devices",
            "Isolates"
        ],
        "answer": "Rounds"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is a Social Networking Service primarily used for non-social interpersonal communication?",
        "options": [
            "Instagram",
            "Reddit",
            "LinkedIn",
            "Twitter! X"
        ],
        "answer": "LinkedIn"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who coined the term \"Infosphere\"?",
        "options": [
            "Delphi",
            "Likert",
            "Luciano Floridi",
            "Brophy"
        ],
        "answer": "Luciano Floridi"
    },
    {
        "question": "The word \"Data\" was originated from the word:",
        "options": [
            "Greek",
            "Latin",
            "Spanish",
            "Persian"
        ],
        "answer": "Latin"
    },
    {
        "question": "Belkin is associated with:",
        "options": [
            "Cataloging",
            "Classification",
            "Documentation",
            "Information theory"
        ],
        "answer": "Information theory"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who coined the term \"Invisible college\"?",
        "options": [
            "B.C. Brooks",
            "Peter Drucker",
            "J.H. Shera",
            "Diana Crane"
        ],
        "answer": "Diana Crane"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is an implication of the first law of library science?",
        "options": [
            "Compact shelving",
            "Library extension service",
            "Location of the library",
            "Implementation of the library act"
        ],
        "answer": "Location of the library"
    },
    {
        "question": "The first library act was enacted by:",
        "options": [
            "Congress of the United States",
            "British Parliament",
            "German Parliament",
            "Russian Governing Council"
        ],
        "answer": "British Parliament"
    },
    {
        "question": "Library pilgrimages are an example of:",
        "options": [
            "Saraswati Pooja during Navaratri",
            "Adult education program",
            "Library cooperation",
            "Library extension service"
        ],
        "answer": "Library extension service"
    },
    {
        "question": "The first-ever library school in the world was started by:",
        "options": [
            "Charles Ammi Cutter",
            "A.D. Dickinson",
            "Melvil Dewey",
            "James Kaiser"
        ],
        "answer": "Melvil Dewey"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is an analytical information source?",
        "options": [
            "Dictionary",
            "Almanac",
            "Directory",
            "Monograph"
        ],
        "answer": "Monograph"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is a neo-conventional source of information?",
        "options": [
            "Atlas",
            "Patent",
            "Audio-visual",
            "Microform"
        ],
        "answer": "Patent"
    }
]